Marcel Breuer Papers
Marcel Breuer Papers
1920-2001
Breuer, Marcel, 1902-1981.
684 linear feet
Papers of the Modernist architect and designer, includes architectural drawings, photographs and slides, project files, writings, correspondence and other materials related to every phase of Marcel Breuer's career.
148864
Biographical History
Marcel Breuer (1902-1981) was a Hungarian-born, American Modernist architect and designer.
Marcel Breuer was born on May 21, 1902 in the southwestern Hungarian city of Pecs. His family home at 4 Irgalmasok Boulevard near Szechenyi square may have afforded a view of the nearby Pasha Qasim mosque (built from the ruins of a Gothic church), or the four landmark towers of the nearby Pecs Cathedral. Noted historically for its diverse ethnic population, Pecs had long been a regional cultural center and a university town (home of the 5th oldest university in Europe), as well as an important religious center, and it is possible that Breuer’s father Jakab Breuer, a dental technician from Gyor, Hungary, had received his training at the university’s medical school. Breuer’s mother, Franciska Kann (sometimes given as “Kan”) came originally from Budapest, and Breuer had two older siblings, Alexander and Hermina Maria.
Always reticient about the facts of his early life, Breuer’s formative years must have been clouded by the violent political conflicts that defined the era. He would have been just twelve years old when Hungary entered World War I as part of the Austro-Hungarian/German alliance (incidentally, Breuer’s subsequent architectural mentor and partner, Walter Gropius, was severly wounded in 1914 while serving as a German reservist on the Western Front). From 1918-1920, the Baranyi region surrounding Breuer’s home town was heavily occupied by Serbian forces who, on the basis of ethnic nationalism, had made significant territorial claims there (tentatively resolved by the Treaty of Trianon in 1920). Against this backdrop, Breuer attended secondary school at Pecsi Allami Forealiskola where he excelled at art and mathematics, graduating summa cum laude and earning a scholarship to the Akademie der bildenden Kunst in Vienna.
Breuer arrived in Vienna in the late summer of 1920, but he would not remain for long. Recognizing immediately that the Viennese institution was a poor fit for his practical orientation, he quickly abandoned the academy, taking up an apprecticeship in the shop of a local cabinetmaker named Bolek. It was during this brief respite that Breuer learned about an innovative new school in Weimar from a fellow Hungarian, the Pecs born architect Fred Forbat. Within a few weeks, Breuer had assumed a place as one of the 143 students enrolled at the Bauhaus in only the second year of its formative existence.
While there is some uncertainty as to exactly when Breuer began his studies at the Bauhaus during the fall of 1920, it is very likely that he arrived about six weeks into the term and began in the Vorkurs, or Preliminary Course, then taught by Johannes Itten. Later that year, he would have done work in the carpentry workshop under Walter Gropius, the Master of Form for the shop at that time, Johannes Itten, and Josef Zachmann, the shop’s first Master of Craft. While many of the personal relationships forged during these years were crucial for Breuer’s artistic development, perhaps none more so that his career-defining linkage with Walter Gropius, it was quite possibly the painter Paul Klee who exerted the most formative influence (later in life, Breuer recollected that Klee had been one of the two most important teachers in his life, the other being his high school geometry teacher). As Franciscono contends, in his history of the school, his [Klee’s] lessons were conceived in terms closely analogous to those of architecture…painting itself was understood as a construction built up or put together from repeatable, more or less geometric—in effect modular—units in ways generally comparable to the way architecture is put together (quoted in Hyman, p.61, n.73).
The practical side of Breuer’s training at the Bauhaus came largely through apprentice work done in Walter Gropius’ active architectural practice, as the school offered no formalized architectural program during those early years. As such, Breuer gained much hands-on experience on a number of projects—contributing furniture and interior designs to the collaborative Sommerfeld House project (1921), the Haus am Horn exhibition house (1923), and the Bauhaussiedlung housing project (planned 1922, but not built).
After completing his apprentice work at the Bauhaus, Breuer headed to Paris, eventually landing a position as a designer for a short time in the office of Pierre Chareau around September 1924. By the following year, though, he was back in Weimar, to accept a position as instructor and head of the furniture and carpentry shop at the Bauhaus, just prior to its official relocation to Dessau. In additional to involvement in furniture and interior design work for the new Bauhaus buildings in Dessau—contributing to the design and furnishing of the canteen, theatre and several of the Master’s Houses—Breuer also developed innovative architectural schemes for a series of houses for junior faculty members, known as the BAMBOS houses (1927), but these were not built.
It was during this second Bauhaus period (1925-1928), that Breuer began to make the innovative experiments with bent tubular steel furniture for which he became so famous. The first version of his iconic “B3” club chair was developed around 1925, and many experiments with cantilevered steel constructions rapidly followed. In 1926, Breuer established the Standard Möbel company and began marketing a full line of steel furniture. Later that year, Breuer married fellow Bauhaus graduate Marta Erps, a talented artist who had studied in the weaving workshop and collaborated with Breuer on the Haus am Horm interiors. Their marriage seems to have been short lived, as Erps left Germany sometime around 1928-1929 for Brazil, where she later had a successful career as a biologist and illustrator at the University of Sao Paolo. Breuer and Erps were officially divorced in 1934.
As internal politics at the Bauhaus grew increasingly volatile in the late 1920s, Breuer joined a major exodus from the school, following Gropius, Moholy-Nagy, Josef Albers, Herbert Bayer and others out of Dessau. Breuer made his way to Berlin, officially joining the Bund Deutscher Architekten and setting up an architectural practice with a former student, Gustav Hassenpflug as his draftsman. His commissions were small, primarily apartment interiors and shops, but he also completed a number of formalized designs for competitions and was represented at many important exhibitions of the period, including the Weissenhof estate exhibition (1928), the Paris exposition of 1930 and the Berlin Building exhibition of 1931. In 1932, Breuer secured his first independent architectural commision to build a modern house in Weisbaden for Paul and Mariane Harnischmacher. During this period, Breuer also maintained a parnership in Budapest with Farkas Molnar and Jozsef Fischer and traveled extensively through southern Europe and North Africa. In 1935, with the assistance of Gropius, Breuer secured papers to relocate to London, where he practiced for a short time in partnership with British architect F.R.S. Yorke, while independently developing a line of bent plywood furniture that was marketed through Jack Pritchard’s Isokon Control Ltd.
Frustrated by the limited building prospects in England and always concerned about the possibility of political deportation, in 1937 Breuer was again on the move. The efforts of Gropius were once more instrumental, as he was able to help secure Breuer a faculty position at Harvard University’s Graduate School of Design. Aesthetically, Breuer was well suited to his new environment, sharing with his fellow Bauhaus emigres a strong appreciation for the structural transparency and efficient design of American industrial buildings. The strong appeal of the traditional New England domestic architecture, though, with its reliance on native stone and balloon-frame construction was perhaps not entirely anticipated. It did prove to be inspirational, as Breuer spent roughly the next decade making his mark with a series of iconic modern houses spread across Massachussets, Connecticut, Pennsylvania and New York (for more on the influence of American domestic architecture on Breuer’s mid-century work, see Bergdall, Encountering America: Marcel Breuer and the Discourses of the Vernacular from Budapest to Boston, in Marcel Breuer: Design and Architecture).
Initially, Breuer praticed in the U.S. in partnership with his long-time mentor under the official designation, “Walter Gropius and Marcel Breuer, Architects.” The partnership was fruitful, architecturally speaking, during lean economic years, producing a series of now canonical houses, including the Frank House in Pittsburgh (1939), the Hagerty House in Cohasset (1938) and, of course, the Ford (1939), Gropius (1938) and Breuer (1939) houses at the Woods End colony in Lincoln, Massachussets.
The Gropius-Breuer partnership ceased in 1941, and Breuer set-up shop on his own in Cambridge with the aid of several of his former students who served as draftsmen. Although work came slowly at first—building supply shortages during the war made new construction a difficult endeavor—by the mid 1940s, the Breuer office was operating at full capacity. In the spring of 1946, Breuer took several of his Cambridge cohorts to New York, opening a practice there on 438 East Eighty-Eighth Street. The subsequent phase of work in the late 1940s marked the pinnacle of Breuer’s domestic architectural production. Working from his fundamental conception of the “bi-nuclear” arrangement of living areas, Breuer progressively refined his design vocabulary into a popular signature style. Stand-out designs of this period include the Geller (1945), Robinson (1948) and Thompson (1949) houses, as well and the House in the Museum Garden, constructed for a 1949 MoMA exhibition on the modern house.
The 1950s saw the exponential growth of Breuer’s creative prospects and subsequent emergence internationaly as a seminal figure of modern design (one of the canonical “form-givers” of the twentieth century, as dubbed in a 1956 Time magazine piece). In an astonishing creative outburst, encompassing roughly the ten year span from 1953-1963, Breuer saw the realization of the half-dozen or so masterworks most definitive of his major phase: the UNESCO headquarters in Paris (1953), Saint John’s Abbey Church in Minnesota (1953-1958), the De Bijenkorpf Department Store in Rotterdam (1953), the United States Embassy at the Hague (1956), the IBM Research Center in La Gaude, France (1960), and the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York (1963). Breuer’s work during this period is largely defined by the transition from small-form, residential projects in wood and stone, to monumental sculptural forms rendered in patterned concrete and steel.
In 1956, in order to accommodate the rapid boom in large-project commissions coming into his office, Breuer sought to formalize a partnership agreement with several of the young and talented architects in his employ. Stipulating a formative ten year period under the designation “associate”, Breuer promised eventual full partnerships to his colleagues. Operating thereafter as Marcel Breuer and Associates, by 1967 Herbert Beckhard, Hamilton Smith and Robert Gatje had all achieved full partner status (former partner Murray Emslie had left the firm in 1965). Later, Tician Papchristou also achieved partner status in the firm.
By the mid-sixties, Breuer had settled his oprations at 635 Madison Avenue in New York, and had opened a much needed European office on the Rue Chapon in the former garment district of Paris, an office edstablished by Bob Gatje and later run by Mario Jossa to manage projects at Flaine, the ZUP development in Bayonne and elsewhere on the continent. Breuer’s working methods with his partners had formalized over many years into a rationalized and highly productive arrangement. Typically, one of the partners would be assigned to a particular project as “job captain”, while Breuer, in addition to formulating the essential design concepts, would serve as an executive presence, overseeing the progress of the many diverse and complicated projects, directing strategy and arbitrating the inevitable conflicts. This working process proved to be quite effective over many years, producing a formidable roster of works: with Robert Gatje, the IBM France complex, the Flaine resort, the Armstrong Rubber Building; with Hamilton Smith, Annunciation Priory, the Whitney Museum of Art, the Grand Coulee Dam Project; with Herbert Beckhard, the HUD and HEW buildings in Washington, D.C. and the Church and Refectory of St. Francis de Sales).
The effects on Breuer of many years of incessant work and travel began to show by the early 1970s, and after a harrowing trip to Afghanistan that saw Breuer suffer a nearly fatal heart attack, his day-to-day working role in his firm significantly diminished. Breuer’s declining health coincided with a difficult economic climate for building; regardless, Marcel Breuer and Associates continued to realize significant building projects throughout the seventies, including the Atlanta Public Library (1971-1980), the American Press Institute in Reston, Virgina (1971), and the Australian Embassy in Paris (1973). These years also saw the realization of two late-phase Breuer jewels—the third Stillman House (1972) and the stunning slate-roofed Chapel at Flaine (1974-1976). Despite his formal retirement on March 1, 1976, Breuer refused to abandon work altogether, vowing in correspondence to his supervising architect at Baldegg Convent that he would personally carry that job through to the end. The last decade of Breuer’s life saw a number of prominent honors and exhibitions of his work. In addition to an honorary doctorate from the Budapest Technical University in 1970, there were major exhibitions at MoMA (1981) and at the Bauhaus-Archiv Museum in 1975 (the first exhibition of his work in Germany since his days at the Bauhaus), as well as a major retrospective exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York (1972-1973), the first ever one-man architectural show in the Met’s history.
[in addition to material from the collection, this account relied on: Isabelle Hyman, Marcel Breuer, Architect: The Career and the Buildings; Christopher Wilk, Marcel Breuer: Furniture and Interiors; Robert F. Gatje, Marcel Breuer: A Memoir]
Breuer’s Offices/Partnerships
Marcel Breuer, Architekt, Berlin (1928-1931)
Marcel Breuer, Farkas Molnar and Joszef Fischer (1933-c. 1935)
Marcel Breur and F.R.S. Yorke, Architects, London (1935-1937)
Walter Gropius and Marcel Breuer, Architects, Cambridge (c. Oct 1937-Aug 1941)
Marcel Breuer, Architect, Cambridge (Aug 1941-c. May 1946)
Marcel Breuer, Architect, 438 East Eighty-Eighth Street, NY (c. May 1946-Sep 1948)
Marcel Breuer, Architect, 113 East Thirty-Seventh Street, NY (Sep 1948-Aug 1956)
Marcel Breuer and Associates, Architects, 201 East Fifty-Seventh Street, NY (Aug 1956-Jun 1965)
Marcel Breuer, Architecte, Paris (Nov 1964)
Marcel Breuer and Associates, Architects, 635 Madison Avenue, NY (Jun 1965-Mar 1978)
Marcel Breuer Associates (MBA), 635 Madison Avenue, NY (Mar 1978)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Marcel Breuer Papers collects over sixty years of work product generated by a prolific international architecural practice spanning most of the twentieth century. The comprehensive collection includes architectural drawings, photographs, project files, published materials, writings, interviews and other materials from every phase of Marcel Breuer’s long and distinguished career. In addition, the collection contains biographical material, material related to Breuer’s teaching days at Harvard University’s Graduate School of Design, and material representing his many professional endeavors including awards, exhibitions, writings on architecture and correspondence with artists, architects, editors and clients.
The Project Records series contains the vast bulk of the collection and consists of architectural drawings, project files (correspondence, specifications, financial records, product literature), published materials and photographs documenting the process of architectural design development, project construction and subsequent presentation/reception of completed projects. The extent of documentation varies by project, but the entirety of Breuer’s career is represented, including his earliest architectural work at the Bauhaus (1923-1928), his subsequent work as an independent architect in Berlin (1928-1931), his work in Budapest in partnership with Farkas Molnár and Jozsef Fischer (1933-1935), his work in London in partnersip with F.R.S. Yorke (1935-1937), his early work in the U.S. in partnership with Walter Gropius (1937-1941) and, by far the majority of the collection, his work as an independent architect and head of the firm Marcel Breuer and Associates (1941-1976). In addition, the collection contains significant project work accomplished by the firm Marcel Breuer and Associates after Breuer’s retirement in 1976, as well as work completed by his associates under the name MBA after his death in 1980. (See Biographical History above for additional information on Breuer’s associated firms and partnerships).
The Professional Records series collects material related to Breuer’s professional endeavors as an architect and includes records related to awards, exhibitions and juries, as well as non-project related correspondence with important artists, architects, editors and patrons. Additional project related material can be found in the writings and publications subseries, and in the scrapbooks of press clippings and memorabilia that Breuer maintained through the 1940s. Material in the Personal Papers series ranges from Breuer’s days as an instructor at the Bauhaus in Dessau to the centenary celebration of his birth held at St. John’s University in 2001/2002. The bulk of the material consists of financial records from his early years in the United States (1937-1943). Faculty Papers contains administrative and course material from Breuer's years on the faculty of the Graduate School of Design at Harvard University (1939-1948). The vast bulk of the Office Records series consists of interoffice correspondence between Breuer’s New York and Paris offices between the years 1964-1978. In addition, there are financial documents and bills, most of which date from the late 1930s to the early 1950s (including small amounts of material from the Breuer-Yorke and Breuer-Gropius partnerships), and extensive travel files (1938-1970) documenting travel arrangements, schedules, contact lists and itineraries for Breuer’s many travels during these years. The Administrative Records sub-series includes the Marcel Breuer and Associates partnership agreement and miscellaneous files related to Breuer’s architectural licenses.
The Furniture series collects materials related to Breuer’s furniture designs and furniture business dealings. This series contains several hundred original furniture drawings, and represents the four major phases of Breuer’s furniture work—wood, tubular steel, aluminum and bent plywood.. This series also contains Correspondence (1920s-1960s) with manufacturers and distributors of Breuer furniture (Thonet, Embru, Isokon, Gavina), correspondence with patent attorneys and agencies (including patent applications and drawings), as well as financial documents, license agreements and contracts. There are a few files related to furniture design competitions, as well as furniture photographs and slides, articles and clippings. Of special note in the Published Materials series are several early furniture catalogs from Thonet and Wohnbedarf, including the Herbert Bayer designed Wohnbedarf aluminum furniture catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The conceptual structure for arrangment of the collection follows the recommendations advanced in Waverly Lowell and Tawny Ryan Nelb’s guide, Architectural Records: Managing Design and Construction Records (Society of American Archivists: Chicago, 2006). Project identification largely follows the listing in Isabelle Hyman, Marcel Breuer, Architect: The Career and the Buildings
Personal Papers, 1925-2001 (Biographical Material, 1938-2001; Correspondence, 1938-1969; Financial Records, 1934-1954; House Papers, 1935-1951; Legal Documents, 1925-1941; Photographs, 1928-1978). Professional Papers, 1923-1992 (Associations, 1940-1960; Awards and Honors, 1947-1973; Clippings, 1948-1950; Competitions, 1938-1948; Consulting, 1942-1947; Correspondence, 1935-1969; Exhibitions, 1938-1972; Interviews, 1962-1995; Juries and Committees, 1944-1950; Publications, 1929-1982; Reference Files, 1935-1981; Scrapbooks, 1923-1950; Slides (Teaching); Writings, 1923-1970). Faculty Papers, 1939-1948 (Administrative, 1939-1948; Course Material, 1939-1941). Office Records, 1931-1979 (Administrative Records, 1931-1976; Financial Records, 1936-1951; Correspondence, 1937-1979; Miscellaneous Office Material, 1930-c.1959; Prospects, 1938-1956; Travel, 1938-1970). Sketchbooks, circa 1950-1970 (Green Sketchbook; Red Sketchbooks; Misc. Non-project Sketches). Furniture, 1921-1982 (Catalogs and Promotional Materials, 1920s-c.1980; Competitions/Exhibitions, 1936-1982; Correspondence and Business Records, 1932-1977; Legal Documents, 1934-1936; Patent Documents, 1920-1938; Published Material and Writings, 1929-1981; Drawings, 1928-1970s; Photographs, 1921-1948). Project Records, 1922-1982 (subseries for for each project: Drawings; Project Files; Published Material; Photographs).
Subject and Genre Headings
Breuer, Marcel, 1902-1981; Marcel Breuer Associates.; Architects -- United States.; Architectural design.; Architectural drawing -- 20th century -- United States.; Architectural firms.; Architectural practice.; Architecture -- United States.; Architecture -- Designs and plans.; Architecture, American.; Architecture, Domestic.; Architecture, Industrial.; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century.; Church architecture -- United States.; Furniture design -- United States.; Furniture designers.; Architectural drawings.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material
Inventory
- Personal Papers, 1925-2001 (inclusive); 1937-1943 (bulk); 3 linear feet
  - Biographical Material, 1938-2001
    - Biographical Sketches/Notes, 1938-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Personal Effects
      - Passports, 1947-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Driving permits, 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Immunization records, membership cards and misc., 1942-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Address book, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Breuer-Words crib sheet, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Connie Breuer items, 1942-1969; driving permits, travel documents, father’s obituary notice and clippings (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Martha Erps (Breuer) items, 1939; 1947; handwritten note (MB) and book invoice (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Memorial Service Registry, Whitney Museum of American Art., 21 Sep 1981; 1 bound volume (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Articles (Obituaries/Retrospective)
      - Emlékezés Breuer Marcelra by József Fischer, Magyar Ėpítőművészet. Jun 1981. pgs. 60-63. [Hungarian] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Marcel Lajos Breuer as He is Remembered, AIA Journal. Aug 1981, p. 11-12. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Marcel Breuer, 1902-1981, Bulletin of the Whitney Museum of American Art. 1981-1982. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Breuer: Saint John’s Celebrates Marcel Breuer, Architect. 2001. (pamphlet) (Box 1, Folder 14)